<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Developer&#39;s notes</title>
    <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Developer&#39;s notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:37:33 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1632296253</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1632296253/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1632296253/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;d found that ping utility on Ubuntu 20.04 and Ubuntu 21.04 works without root permissions, suid flag, or CAP_NET_RAW capability. In the [Kernel documentation](The sysctl documentation writes) it is said that ping uses ICMP_PROTO datagram sockets and it&amp;rsquo;s possible to allow users without root permissions to create such sockets:
 ping_group_range - 2 INTEGERS
  Restrict ICMP_PROTO datagram sockets to users in the group range. The default is &amp;ldquo;1 0&amp;rdquo;, meaning, that nobody (not even root) may create ping sockets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1631610988</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631610988/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 09:16:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631610988/</guid>
      <description>I use Thunderbird as an e-mail client. I&amp;rsquo;d configured several rules on the server side for splitting messages from INBOX into several folders (Jira, GitLab, etc.). It&amp;rsquo;s important to execute these rules on the server side because I have several clients and, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to make the same rules for each client. By default, Thunderbird checks only the INBOX folder of the IMAP account, so I had no notifications about new mail in the other folders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1631122832</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631122832/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 17:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631122832/</guid>
      <description>There is a Full HD screen on my 14&amp;quot; laptop. It looks like some sort of HiDPI for me, and that is why controls of an interface on native resolution are too small, so it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to use. On Windows, an interface was scaled for 125% and looks a lot better.
I tried to make the same settings on Ubuntu 21.04, and there were some issues. There are two options: a new Wayland session and a more traditional Xorg session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630740946</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630740946/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 07:35:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630740946/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve used to ask questions about different open source projects on Freenode IRC several years ago. Today I&amp;rsquo;ve found that Freenode staff members had left the company and started Libera.Chat. You can find the roots of this decision on Wiki page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630503528</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630503528/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 13:38:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630503528/</guid>
      <description>Recently Docker has updated subscriptions, and now Docker Desktop remains free only for individuals or small businesses. I think it&amp;rsquo;s OK that Docker as a company wants to get money from their products. At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s a bit strange to change the rules of the game for existing products. We&amp;rsquo;ll see how the community reacts to this announcement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630395790</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630395790/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 07:43:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630395790/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important parts of laptop security is disk encryption. It can help to save your personal data if you lost your computer or it was stolen. It&amp;rsquo;s impossible to encrypt everything. You need some code to ask for the password from the user and decrypt the system.
There are several options when you work with Ubuntu:
 encrypt only home directory; encrypt the operating system partition during the installation process and rely on UEFI Secure Boot for Linux kernel verification; encrypt not only the operating system partition, but also the boot partition; look at Full Disk Encryption Howto for more details.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630181380</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630181380/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 20:09:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630181380/</guid>
      <description>I have been using macOS on the laptop for a few years, but recently I switched back to Ubuntu. It has several advantages for my usage pattern: the environment which my programs use in production, Docker with fast FS and without imposed updates, and a lot more control over the system.
One thing that I miss is Time Machine. Having up-to-date backups is extremely important. It helps when your computer stops working normally, or it has been stolen, or you just want to move from one laptop to another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630170209</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630170209/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 17:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630170209/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I find interesting links or have some thoughts about software engineering problems that I want to save and share. It&amp;rsquo;s not enough for an article in the blog, so I don&amp;rsquo;t publish it there. That is why I&amp;rsquo;d created this page, and I&amp;rsquo;m going to post some short messages here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630067102</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630067102/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 12:25:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630067102/</guid>
      <description>Hello world!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
