<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Developer&#39;s notes</title>
    <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Developer&#39;s notes</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 06:30:08 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>1656743408</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1656743408/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jul 2022 06:30:08 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1656743408/</guid>
      <description>One task that I perform these days is the configuration of the FreeIPA domain. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s not trivial, so I need to debug some sort of quirky errors from time to time. Today I&amp;rsquo;d found Thomas C. Foulds&amp;rsquo;s blog that contains a lot of useful information about FreeIPA debugging. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely worth reading.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1654367223</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1654367223/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jun 2022 18:27:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1654367223/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s possible to connect to a remote host over SSH using a public key. It&amp;rsquo;s a well-known feature which I use every day. SSH protocol is also used for the git clone command. I was curious about how Gitea implements the support of the SSH protocol. The first idea was about the custom SSH server. I&amp;rsquo;d inspected my local Gitea installation and found that there was no custom SSH server running, just the default sshd.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1653742728</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1653742728/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 May 2022 12:58:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1653742728/</guid>
      <description>Ubuntu 22.04 distributes Firefox as a snap package. It starts slower than Firefox installed as a deb-package and it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to control updates of the browser. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to install Firefox as a deb package from Mozilla Team PPA. There is a useful guide from omgubuntu.co.uk about how to configure the system to use this PPA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1652165698</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1652165698/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 06:54:58 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1652165698/</guid>
      <description>Most of RPM-based Linux distributions use frontends like yum or dnf. Most of deb-based Linux distributions use apt-get, aptitude or apt. Surprisingly, there is an APT-RPM package manager — a version of apt-get modified to work with RPM.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1651653237</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1651653237/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 May 2022 08:33:57 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1651653237/</guid>
      <description>Annoying bug: it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to add a route without a gateway in NetworkManager GUI in Ubuntu 20.04. Fortunately, there is a workaround: use 0.0.0.0 as a gateway.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1651607294</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1651607294/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 19:48:14 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1651607294/</guid>
      <description>Systemd allows to pass a single argument to a service. This feature is called Service Templates. It can be used for such applications as OpenVPN (the argument is a connection config name) or PostgreSQL (the argument is a cluster version).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1650723317</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650723317/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 Apr 2022 14:15:17 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650723317/</guid>
      <description>Kubuntu 22.04 has libssl 3.0.2, that is not compatible with libssl from old releases, so Viber messenger is not working. It shows an error message &amp;ldquo;No Connection&amp;rdquo; even the other network apps like Firefox work well. I think this bug will be fixed in future Viber versions. For now, it&amp;rsquo;s possible to perform a hotfix:
Install libssl 1.2.1 from Ubuntu 21.10:
wget http://security.ubuntu.com/ubuntu/pool/main/o/openssl/libssl1.1_1.1.1l-1ubuntu1.2_amd64.deb sudo dpkg -i libssl1.1_1.1.1l-1ubuntu1.2_amd64.deb Preload libssl 1.2.1 into Viber.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1650661745</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650661745/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 21:09:05 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650661745/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve just updated from Kubuntu 21.04 to Kubuntu 22.04 on my laptop. From the release notes I found no breaking changes, but only minor updates for different programs. Everything works as expected.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1650613842</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650613842/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2022 07:50:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650613842/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s convenient to monitor network activity in the terminal. There are several tools for this task: bmon, slurm or tcptrack. I prefer to use slurm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1650372413</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650372413/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Apr 2022 12:46:53 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650372413/</guid>
      <description>Some people prefer to use self-hosting services instead of consuming from SaaSS providers. It&amp;rsquo;s useful to look through the comprehensive list of different software which can be hosted on your own server.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1650186560</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650186560/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 09:09:20 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650186560/</guid>
      <description>What’s The Deal With Snap Packages? Snap package system offers a controversial approach for managing software. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely not a silver bullet. Two years ago I wrote an article with such a point of view and today I&amp;rsquo;ve found an article that shares my point of view in some way. It&amp;rsquo;s definitely worth reading. I think the user should control the system and package manager should allow to do it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1650184950</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650184950/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Apr 2022 08:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1650184950/</guid>
      <description>KernelNewbies is an extremely useful resource for those who want to explore kernel changes but yet not ready for reading lkml.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1649939747</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1649939747/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Apr 2022 12:35:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1649939747/</guid>
      <description>From time to time I have to check my disk usage. It&amp;rsquo;s possible to use df and du for rough estimate, but it&amp;rsquo;s more convenient to have some UI for further analysis. I prefer to use ncdu. Some other tools are described in the article.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1649006347</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1649006347/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Apr 2022 17:19:07 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1649006347/</guid>
      <description>OpenSnitch is a GNU/Linux port of the Little Snitch application firewall. Tried it today on Kubuntu 21.04. It works as expected, so if you got used to Little Snitch on MacOS and switched to Linux you should definitely give it a chance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1648910196</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1648910196/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 14:36:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1648910196/</guid>
      <description>Looked at Gitea as a self-hosted alternative for GitHub. It looks nice: a lot of useful features like global code search and template repositories. There is a comprehensive comparison of Gitea to other Git hosting solutions. It can help decide if Gitea is suited for your needs or not.
The only thing that surprised me a bit: the information about package registry is already in the official docs, but PR with this feature was merged only several days ago, so it will be available only in v1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1648796908</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1648796908/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 07:08:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1648796908/</guid>
      <description>Surprisingly found that Linux has multiple routing tables and set of rules that tell the kernel how to choose the particular table for each packet. There are an article and a reddit discussion explaining this subject.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1648670838</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1648670838/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Mar 2022 20:07:18 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1648670838/</guid>
      <description>Today I&amp;rsquo;ve created a test stand that consisted of several Debian VMs to learn some basic network management and firewall and VPN configuration. It looks astonishing. My primary job is writing software, that is why I configure Linux networks rarely, and it&amp;rsquo;s a bit complicated for me. Maybe a bit later I&amp;rsquo;ll write an article about all this stuff.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1646983221</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1646983221/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2022 07:20:21 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1646983221/</guid>
      <description>Really awesome video about hacking the Nintendo Game &amp;amp; Watch. It uses STM32 locked processor and AES-CTR encrypted flash, but it had not helped, and the console was hacked one day before release.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1646669969</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1646669969/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 16:19:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1646669969/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;d used CentOS as a production environment for working projects. Some time ago Red Hat announced its plans to replace stable CentOS 8 with rolling release CentOS Stream. So, CentOS had been replaced with Oracle Linux. Today I&amp;rsquo;ve found that Oracle has its own Linux kernel build that is called Unbreakable Enterprise Kernel. They add some features like Ksplice that look interesting for high-load enterprise platforms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1645598791</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1645598791/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Feb 2022 06:46:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1645598791/</guid>
      <description>Unexpectedly discovered a lot of paid proprietary apps in snapcraft. I think it&amp;rsquo;s great because Linux users and developers have more choices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1645221056</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1645221056/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Feb 2022 21:50:56 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1645221056/</guid>
      <description>Do you feel like you getting old and new technologies do not excite you anymore? Do you think that you have seen most things before? I&amp;rsquo;ve found an interesting discussion on Hacker News about this topic. Different people share their feelings and ways of getting through this period of life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1644658585</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1644658585/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Feb 2022 09:36:25 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1644658585/</guid>
      <description>Falling down the rabbit hole of HiDPI screens and fractional scaling on Linux desktops I came across an interesting discussion on Reddit. It contains a lot of useful links that help to form an opinion on the subject.
I found that in the KDE X11 session fractional scaling is implemented on Qt Framework level, so each app scales its output itself. Gnome uses a different technique. It implies rendering everything at an integer factor and then downscaling using a raster operation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1644617329</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1644617329/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Feb 2022 22:08:49 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1644617329/</guid>
      <description>The majority of GUI apps on Linux are written using some toolkit like GTK or Qt. Such libs provide high-level abstractions like buttons or labels but the real rendering is executed on the backend like X11 or Wayland. I&amp;rsquo;d never thought about it. Today I&amp;rsquo;ve found that the X11 backend uses Xlib. To understand what level of abstraction GUI libraries provide, you can take a look at this small tutorial. After writing a Hello World with Xlib it becomes clear for me why developers introduce more abstraction layers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1644078399</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1644078399/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 16:26:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1644078399/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m learning the STM32 platform. The code generation in STM32CubeIDE makes it easier to configure different MCU subsystems and start writing &amp;ldquo;hello world&amp;rdquo; apps. However, it can be difficult to understand how all this magic works. Fortunately, there is a comprehensive explanation in the STM32CubeMX for STM32 configuration and initialization C code generation user manual in section 6.1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1643143370</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1643143370/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 20:42:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1643143370/</guid>
      <description>To make L2TP/IPsec VPN client work under Kubuntu install network-manager-l2tp package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1643060990</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1643060990/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jan 2022 21:49:50 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1643060990/</guid>
      <description>Today I&amp;rsquo;ve found that youtube-dl downloads video too slow. Switching to yt-dlp helped: 10MiB/s instead of 50KiB/s.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1641756063</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1641756063/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Jan 2022 19:21:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1641756063/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago I&amp;rsquo;d bought Focusrite Scarlett gen3 audio interface because it&amp;rsquo;s one of the devices that work on Linux out of the box. Unfortunately, some features of the device can be accessed only through Focusrite Control that is not available on Linux. Recently I&amp;rsquo;d found an interesting stream about improving Focusrite Scarlett Driver that shows how to access additional features of the device on the Linux platform. It is worth watching if you are interested in reverse engineering and Linux drivers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1641155092</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1641155092/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 20:24:52 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1641155092/</guid>
      <description>I have a network smb share with different videos that I want to watch over network on my devices. Today I&amp;rsquo;d tried to watch a video on my Kubuntu laptop with VLC. It prints errors like:
Your input can&#39;t be opened: VLC is unable to open the MRL &#39;smb://10.0.0.1/Share/video.mkv&#39;. Check the log for details. I&amp;rsquo;d checked logs and found nothing. I&amp;rsquo;d tried to set username and password in the settings as suggested on the Internet with no results.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1640974351</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1640974351/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 18:12:31 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1640974351/</guid>
      <description>Today I&amp;rsquo;ve found Albert. It&amp;rsquo;s a great Alfred-like app for Linux.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1638453327</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1638453327/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 13:55:27 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1638453327/</guid>
      <description>Zoom has become the de facto standard for online communications for me. On Linux Zoom depends on ibus. It looks a bit strange because Zoom works fine without this dependency and in some cases, ibus can make problems. There is a nice article about how to repack Zoom to work without ibus.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1638126669</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1638126669/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 19:11:09 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1638126669/</guid>
      <description>Recently, I&amp;rsquo;ve found a page, explaining the types of packages in Ubuntu. It gives the information about strengths and weaknesses of each packaging system and discusses what is the best choice for different usage scenarios. The article gives me a lot to think about. Although certain solutions seem controversial to me, the article clarifies the vision of Canonical for package systems.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1637445162</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1637445162/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Nov 2021 21:52:42 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1637445162/</guid>
      <description>Is it time to switch from Docker to Podman?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1637062416</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1637062416/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Nov 2021 11:33:36 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1637062416/</guid>
      <description>I have a dual boot setup on my PC: Ubuntu and Windows 10. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s required to reload Windows for processing system updates. By default, Grub loads the first system from the list, which is Ubuntu. It&amp;rsquo;s inconvenient. I think it&amp;rsquo;s better to make Grub remember the last loaded OS and start it after reboot.
To achieve this behaviour you need to perform such steps:
  Add to /etc/default/grub following strings:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1634247448</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1634247448/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Oct 2021 21:37:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1634247448/</guid>
      <description>Found KDE Timeline. Looks interesting. The times of KDE 3 were really awesome.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1632296253</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1632296253/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:37:33 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1632296253/</guid>
      <description>Recently I&amp;rsquo;d found that ping utility on Ubuntu 20.04 and Ubuntu 21.04 works without root permissions, suid flag, or CAP_NET_RAW capability. In the Kernel documentation it is said that ping uses ICMP_PROTO datagram sockets and it&amp;rsquo;s possible to allow users without root permissions to create such sockets:
 ping_group_range - 2 INTEGERS
  Restrict ICMP_PROTO datagram sockets to users in the group range. The default is &amp;ldquo;1 0&amp;rdquo;, meaning, that nobody (not even root) may create ping sockets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1631610988</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631610988/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Sep 2021 09:16:28 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631610988/</guid>
      <description>I use Thunderbird as an e-mail client. I&amp;rsquo;d configured several rules on the server side for splitting messages from INBOX into several folders (Jira, GitLab, etc.). It&amp;rsquo;s important to execute these rules on the server side because I have several clients and, I don&amp;rsquo;t want to make the same rules for each client. By default, Thunderbird checks only the INBOX folder of the IMAP account, so I had no notifications about new mail in the other folders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1631122832</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631122832/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 17:40:32 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1631122832/</guid>
      <description>There is a Full HD screen on my 14&amp;quot; laptop. It looks like some sort of HiDPI for me, and that is why controls of an interface on native resolution are too small, so it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to use. On Windows, an interface was scaled for 125% and looks a lot better.
I tried to make the same settings on Ubuntu 21.04, and there were some issues. There are two options: a new Wayland session and a more traditional Xorg session.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630740946</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630740946/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 07:35:46 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630740946/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve used to ask questions about different open source projects on Freenode IRC several years ago. Today I&amp;rsquo;ve found that Freenode staff members had left the company and started Libera.Chat. You can find the roots of this decision on Wiki page.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630503528</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630503528/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 13:38:48 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630503528/</guid>
      <description>Recently Docker has updated subscriptions, and now Docker Desktop remains free only for individuals or small businesses. I think it&amp;rsquo;s OK that Docker as a company wants to get money from their products. At the same time, it&amp;rsquo;s a bit strange to change the rules of the game for existing products. We&amp;rsquo;ll see how the community reacts to this announcement.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630395790</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630395790/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Aug 2021 07:43:10 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630395790/</guid>
      <description>One of the most important parts of laptop security is disk encryption. It can help to save your personal data if you lost your computer or it was stolen. It&amp;rsquo;s impossible to encrypt everything. You need some code to ask for the password from the user and decrypt the system.
There are several options when you work with Ubuntu:
 encrypt only home directory; encrypt the operating system partition during the installation process and rely on UEFI Secure Boot for Linux kernel verification; encrypt not only the operating system partition, but also the boot partition; look at Full Disk Encryption Howto for more details.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630181380</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630181380/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 20:09:40 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630181380/</guid>
      <description>I have been using macOS on the laptop for a few years, but recently I switched back to Ubuntu. It has several advantages for my usage pattern: the environment which my programs use in production, Docker with fast FS and without imposed updates, and a lot more control over the system.
One thing that I miss is Time Machine. Having up-to-date backups is extremely important. It helps when your computer stops working normally, or it has been stolen, or you just want to move from one laptop to another.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630170209</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630170209/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 17:03:29 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630170209/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I find interesting links or have some thoughts about software engineering problems that I want to save and share. It&amp;rsquo;s not enough for an article in the blog, so I don&amp;rsquo;t publish it there. That is why I&amp;rsquo;d created this page, and I&amp;rsquo;m going to post some short messages here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>1630067102</title>
      <link>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630067102/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 12:25:02 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://notes.0e39bf7b.blog/posts/1630067102/</guid>
      <description>Hello world!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
